John Cropper Correspondence, 1776-1838
Mortimer Rare Book Room, William Allan Neilson Library, Smith College
John Cropper correspondence
1776-1838
Cropper, John, 1755-1821
113
1 box (18 items)
Mortimer Rare Book Room Smith College Northampton, MA
Correspondence written by John Cropper while serving as an officer in the Revolutionary War to Marget Cropper, his wife, and Geo. Abbott or received by him from Geo. Corbin and others between 1776 and 1838.
Biographical Note
John Cropper, soldier, was born in Virginia in 1756. Almost a boy at the opening of the struggle of the colonies with the mother-country, and filled with patriotic ardor, he joined the revolutionary forces of 1775, as captain of the 9th Virginia regiment. He was promoted to be major of the 5th, which he lead with great gallantry in the battle of Brandywine under heavy losses, and as colonel of the 7th, he took part in the battles of Germantown and Monmouth. He was made lieutenant colonel of the 11th regiment, May 15, 1778, and subsequently its colonel. He died at Bowman's Folly, Virginia, January 15, 1821.
[From National Cyclopaedia of American Biography, v. 2, p. 189]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John Cropper correspondence consists of 18 letters written by John Cropper to Marget Cropper, his wife, and George Abbot, as well as letters received by him from George Corbin, his uncle, or other individuals. The letters deal with domestic issues of his family life as well as glimpses of the war effort during the Revolutionary War.
These letters were given to the Rare Book Room of Smith College Libraries in memory of John Spencer Bassett by Josephine Whitney Nixon (Smith College Class of 1909) through her daughter, Elizabeth Nixon Roseberry (Smith College Class of 1935) in June 1953. The letters had been preserved by Mrs. Nixon's grandmother, Emma Hopkins Stevenson. There is no known relationship to any of the Cropper family.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
History of the Collection
Search Terms
Cropper, John, 1755-1821.; Cropper, Marget.; Cropper family.; Virginia-Militia-History-Sources.; United States-History-Revolutionary period, 1775-1783-Sources.; Abbot, George.; Corbin, George.
Additional Information
Related Material
John Cropper Papers, 1770-1820 (in Virginia Historical Society, Richmond, Va., Mss1/C8835/a)
Papers of John Cropper, 1778-1814 (in University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Va.)
Cropper, John. Letters from old trunk (Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 45 (1937):40-45)
Cropper John. The Society of the Cincinnati in Virginia (Publications of the Southern History Association 4 (1900:344-350)
Contents List
- Letter from John Cropper to Peggy (Marget Cropper, his wife), Accomack County, Virginia, from Philadelphia, 1777 Jan 16. (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Letter from John Cropper to George Abbot, Accomack County, Virginia, from Morristown, N.J., 1777 Apr 1. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter from George Corbin to John Cropper (Jack), Morristown, N.J., 1777 Apr 30. (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letter from John Cropper to George Abbot ("dear Friend"), Accomack County, Virginia, from Shorthills, N.J., 1777 May 24. There are also paragraphs in this letter that are addressed to his wife, Marget Cropper. (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from George Corbin to John Cropper (Jack), Newark, N.J., from Accomack County, Virginia, 1777 Jun 8. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Letter from George Corbin to John Cropper ("dear Nephew"), 7th Regiment Virginia Regulars, Pennsylvania, from Onancock, 1777 Oct 20. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from John Cropper to George Abbott, Accomack County, Virginia, from Bethlehem, Virginia, 1777 Nov 10. (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Letter from John Cropper to Peggy (Marget Cropper), Accomack County, Virginia, from Camp Valley Forge, 1778 Mar 13. (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letter from John Cropper to Peggy (Marget Cropper), from Camp Valley Forge, 1778 May 10. (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Letter from John Cropper to Peggy (Marget Cropper), from Camp Valley Forge, 1778 May 29. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter from George Corbin ("G. C.") to John Cropper ("my dear Nephew"), from Accomack Country, Virginia, 1778 Jul 18. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Letter from George Corbin to John Cropper ("Johnny"), New Jersey, from Pocomoke, 1778 Jul 21. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Letter from George Corbin to John Cropper ("Dear Sir"), from Morse Town, 1781 Sep 4. (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Letter from Jno Wise to John Cropper ("Dear Sir"), Accomack County, Virginia, from Richmond, 1799 Dec 6. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Letter from Jno Wise to John Cropper ("Dr. Sir"), Accomack County, Virginia, from Richmond, 1799 Dec 11. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letter from Saml Coward, to John Cropper, from Bell Haven, 1807 Jun 28. (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Letter to John Cropper outlining a "program" for a 1809 Jul 4 celebration by an unknown correspondent, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Letter from V. S. Ellis to Mrs. Catherine Cropper, Accomack County, Virginia, from Washington City, 1838 Nov 15. (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Typescripts of the letters including a typescript of a letter not included in the collection: George Corbin to John Cropper ("Dr. Jack"), 1777 Oct 29. (Box 1, Folder 19)